Guide to the Committees of Correspondence (U.S) Records TAM 220
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
Committees of Correspondence (U.S.) Records
1991-1997
TAM 220
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
1.5 linear feet (2 boxes)
The Committees on Correspondence was organized in 1992 after the 1991 CPUSA convention as a non-Leninist, democratic socialist organization to dispute the policies and leadership of CPUSA head, Gus Hall. The movement centered around the respected veteran communist and former leading CP official, Gil Green (1906-1997). The CoC sought to reach out to others on the left outside the Party, and held conferences in 1992 and 1994 to formally establish the new organization. Around 2000, the CoC's name was changed to the Committees of Correspondence for Democracy and Socialism. The collection includes: letters, memos, statements, minutes and emails that document formation of the organization and national leadership meeting minutes.
Committees of Correspondence (U.S.).
Box 1-2
Provenance
Donated by the Committees of Correspondence in February, 2000.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
The late 1980s and early 1990s saw, within the Communist Party of the USA (aka CP or CPUSA), the growth of an informal dissident "Gorbachevite" current, centered around the respected veteran communist and former leading CP official, Gil Green (1906-1997). Prepatory to the CP’s November, 1991 national convention in Cleveland, this group coalesced under the name "Initiative" to dispute the policies and leadership of CP head Gus Hall. After their defeat, which included an acrimonious credentials struggle that saw the Cleveland police called to enforce the rulings of the Gus Hall-dominated convention, the reformers withdrew from the CP and established the Committees of Correspondence (CoC) in 1992 as a non-Leninist, democratic socialist organization. The new group, while composed principally of ex-Communists, sought to reach out to others on the left, and held a conference in San Francisco in July, 1992, preparatory to formally establishing a new organization, which did not occur until the July, 1994 convention in Chicago. The organization’s name was changed, circa 2000, to the Committees of Correspondence for Democracy and Socialism.
Scope and Content Note
The content of this collection reflects the origins of the CoC. Since the split with the CPUSA was in large measure connected to different approaches towards democratic processes within the Party, these procedures take up a lot of room in the discussions. There is also discussion of the meaning and relevance of socialism and socialist ideas in light of the collapse of the Communist bloc. Discussions of the envisioned character of the new organization are in various forms: letters, memos, statements, minutes and emails. The national leadership discussions are documented in detailed minutes and, frequently, hand-written notes by participants; the same is true for the national conventions. Although the CoC consisted of many local branches, it is only the Northern Californians whose activities are reflected here. The correspondence is largely national with some contacts to the international leftist scene.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged chronologically.
The files are grouped into 1 series:
Inventory
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
The Gil Green Papers (Collection number: Tamiment 95)
Separated Material
There is no information about materials that are associated by provenance to the described materials that have been physically separated or removed.
Committees of Correspondence (U.S.).; Committees of Correspondence for Democracy and Socialism.; Communist Party of the United States of America.; Green, Gil, 1906-; Communism |z United States.; Correspondence.; Electronic mail.; Minutes.; Socialism |z United States.
- Inventory
  - Cleveland Meeting of the Initative, Nov 1991 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - From "Initiative" to CoC, Nov 1991-Jan 1992 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Initiative, Oct 1991-Dec 1991 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letters in Response to the Appeal of the "Ad Hoc Committee", 1991 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Notes on the Cleveland-Convention by a Dissident, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - "People’s Weekly World" Lockout, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Post-Cleveland Position Papers of CoC Members, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Statements Concerning the Split, 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1991-1996 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Financial Records, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - CoC-Youth Caucus, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence with Japanese Activist, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - NCC-Minutes, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - NEC-Minutes, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - New York CoC - Meeting, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - San Francisco Conference - Endorsements, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - San Francisco Conference - Reactions and Statements, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - San Francisco Conference - Speeches, Resolutions, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - San Francisco Conference - Workshops, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence with German Activists, 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Kendra Alexander (1946 - 1993), 1992-1994 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - CoC - Regional Initiatives (California), 1992-1996 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence with South African Activists, 1992-1996 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - CoC - Flyers, Invites, 1992-1996 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Press Releases, 1992-1996 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Correspondence, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - NCC-Minutes, Jun 1993 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - NEC-Minutes, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Proposals for Structures and Goals of the CoC, ca.1993 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Correspondence with French Activists, 1993-1994 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Founding Convention Preparation - Delegates, Committees, Tables, 1993-1994 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Rules Committee for the Founding Convention, 1993-1994 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - By Laws Committee, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Co-Chairs, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Convention Advertisement Journals, 1994, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Convention Greetings, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Correspondence, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Correspondence: Post-Convention Thank You Notes, Jul 1994-Aug 1994 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Founding Convention - Speaker Invitations, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Founding Convention - Speeches, Statements, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Name Proposals, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - NCC-Minutes, Jan 1994 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - NCC-Minutes, Nov 1994 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - NEC-Minutes, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Nominations - Convention (with biographies), 1994 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Programmatic Suggestions for CoC and Founding Convention, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Correspondence, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - NCC-Minutes, May 1995 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - NCC-Convention, Dec 1995 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - South Africa Trip, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Co-Chairs, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - CoC-Convention - By Laws, Resolutions, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Convention Arrangements (Invites, Registrations), 1996 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - CoC-Convention - Comments (Post Convention), 1996 (Box 2, Folder 1a)
  - Convention - Cultural Event, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 1b)
  - Convention - Memos, Drafts, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 1c)
  - Convention - Nominations and Elections, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 1 d)
  - Convention Preparations: Workshops, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 1e)
  - Correspondence, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 1g)
  - NCC-Minutes, Mar 1996 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - NCC-Minutes, Dec 1996 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - NEC-Minutes, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - NEC-Minutes, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 4)